Inventory of the Harry Clair Shriver collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Harry Clair Shriver collection
1939-1975
78020
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize box (2.5 linear feet)
Clippings, pamphlets, writings, directives, and regulations, relating to government censorship, propaganda, and civil liberties in the United States during World War II.
Shriver, Harry Clair, 1904-1986
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1978.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical note
Harry C. Shriver (1904-1986) was born near Gettysburg, Pennsylvania. He received his J.D. from George Washington University, and went on to serve as a member of the bar of the District of Columbia and of the United States Supreme Court. Shriver was a government lawyer for a number of federal agencies, including the Library of Congress, the Federal Trade Commission, and the War Shipping Administration. He also served as General Counsel for the Navy Department, Hearing Examiner for the Federal Power Commission in 1963, and Administrative Law Judge in 1972.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains newspaper clippings, codes and regulations, press releases, speeches, pamphlets, reports, and bibliographies collected by Shriver during and after World War II. The contents of this collection focuses on the topics of wartime censorship, propaganda, free speech, and civil liberties. The clippings cover a large portion of the collection and describe the creation of the Office of Censorship and government activity concerning censorship and propaganda throughout the war years, from 1941 to 1947. Other notable documents in the collection include several pamphlets on censorship and war for the general public, wartime regulations for radio, TV broadcasters, and the press, and a copy of the presidential directive establishing the U.S. Office of Censorship. The collection also includes two books authored by Shriver, which are unrelated to World War II, but reflect Shriver's legal career.
Civil rights--United States.; Propaganda, American.; World War, 1939-1945--Censorship.; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
- Correspondence, 1942 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Speeches, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Printed Matter, 1939-1947
  - Bibliographies, 1940 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Censorship and banned books, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    Scope and Contents note
    Comprised of article, correspondence, and a list of banned books
  - Clippings on government censorship, 1941-1947
    Includes clippings on propaganda, free apeech, and civil rights.
    - 1941 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - 1941 September-October (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - 1941 November (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - 1941 December (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - 1941 December 10-17 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - 1941 December 18-27 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - 1942 January (Box-folder 1 :11)
    - 1942 February (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - 1942 March (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - 1942 April (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - 1942 May (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - 1942 June (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - 1942 June 9-16 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - 1942 June 16-20 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - 1942 June 21-25 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - 1942 June 26-30 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - 1942 July (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - 1942 July 1-10 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - 1942 July 11-15 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - 1942 July 16-31 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - 1942 August (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - 1942 August 1-10 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - 1942 September-October (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - 1942 November (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - 1942 December (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - 1943 January (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - 1943 February (Box-folder 3: 11)
    - 1943 March (Box-folder 3: 12)
    - 1943 April (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - 1943 May (Box-folder 3: 14)
    - 1943 June (Box-folder 3: 15)
    - 1943 July (Box-folder 3: 16)
    - 1943 August (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - 1943 September (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - 1943 October (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - 1943 November (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - 1943 December (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - 1944 January (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - 1944 February (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - 1944 March (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - 1944 April (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - 1944 May-August (Box-folder 4: 10)
    - 1945-1947 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Legislation, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - U.S. Office of Censorship: Codes, Regulations, and Press Releases, 1941-1944 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - U.S. Office of War Information: Press Releases and Newsletters, 1942 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Propaganda and Censorship: Articles, Press Releases, and Bibliographies, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Pamphlets, 1939-1943
    - 1939-1941 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - 1942-1943 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Press Releases, 1942 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Reports, 1941-1945 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Books, 1970-1975
    - The Government Lawyer: Essays on Men, Books, and the Law (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - What Gusto: Stories and Anecdotes about Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes, 1970 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - New York Times Magazine, 1942 April 12 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - "The Gestapo," pamphlet, 1941 (Box-folder 6: 2)